Guide to the Marjorie and J. Warren Matson Papers, 1942-1980 AIS.1984.17
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Marjorie and J. Warren Matson Papers
1942-1980
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Matson, J. Warren
AIS.1984.17
12.5 Linear Feet (8 boxes)
This collection contains the records of Marjorie and J. Warren Matson, a couple known for their community involvement. Marjorie Matson (1913-1980), a prominent lawyer and civil libertarian in Pittsburgh, served as Allegheny County solicitor, assistant district attorney, and president of the Pittsburgh Chapter of the American Civil Liberties Union (ACLU). J. Warren Matson (1905-1983), an engineer and social worker, was known for his work for the Housing Authority of the City of Pittsburgh (HACP), as well as community activities on behalf of seniors and other residents of the Hill District. These records detail their work in their respective careers from 1942 to 1980, and cover a broad range of subjects including academic freedom, civil liberties and rights, health care, racial conflicts, the Vietnam War, conscription, housing, juvenile delinquency, prisons, and advocacy for senior citizens.
Biography
Marjorie Matson (1913-1980) was a well-known lawyer and civil libertarian. In 1932, she joined the League for Social Justice and the Women's International League for Peace and Freedom. She was active in the Pennsylvania Security League from 1934 to 1936, which promoted better working conditions in the state, and served as the secretary for the Joint Committee of the Works Progress Administration (WPA). After receiving a law degree from the University of Pittsburgh in 1937, she became an assistant county solicitor in 1941, the first woman in Allegheny County to occupy that position. After World War II she was active in various community organizations, including the Berkely Hills Volunteer Fire Department and the White Oak Heights Women's Club. In 1947 she became an assistant district attorney, another position that had never been occupied by a woman before.
Matson became active in the Pittsburgh Chapter of the American Civil Liberties Union (ACLU) in 1942, and served as the local representative and chair for some years after. The group later recognized her with its first annual Civil Libertarian Award. She was also a member of Americans for Democratic Action and the Allegheny Council on Civil Rights and was involved in several controversial court cases. She took a leave of absence from her job as assistant district attorney in 1950 due to allegations of communist sympathy brought by Charles J. Margiotti, the state attorney general. When the allegations against her were cleared in 1951 she returned to the position until 1952, when Republican James F. Malone became district attorney.
J. Warren Matson (1905-1983) was especially known for his social work and community activities in the Hill District of Pittsburgh. Matson earned an engineering degree in 1933 and a Master's degree in social work in 1938, both from the University of Pittsburgh. During the Depression, Matson spent two years working for the WPA on the Transient Bureau Farm in Butler, Pennsylvania. He was employed as an engineer for the Union Switch Signal Company from 1933 through 1936. In 1939, Matson worked for the probation office of Allegheny County. From 1940-1961, he worked for the Pittsburgh City Housing Authority, dealing with tenant selection problems. Matson founded Hill Opportunity Progress and Education (HOPE), an organization which addressed economic and housing problems in Pittsburgh's Hill District. He also helped to establish the Action Coalition of Elders, an organization which helped provide support services for the elderly.
Scope and Content Notes
The records in this collection show the various causes the Matsons were involved in throughout their careers, such as academic freedom, civil liberties and rights, health care, racial conflicts, the Vietnam War, conscription, housing, juvenile delinquency, prisons, and advocacy for senior citizens. The records, dating from 1942 to 1980, are organized into five series:
Series I. American Civil Liberties Union, Marjorie Matson
Series II. Legal Records of Marjorie Matson
Series III. City Development and Housing, J. Warren Matson
Series IV. Other Civic Involvement of J. Warren Matson
Series V. Subject Files
Series VI. Client Files of Marjorie Matson (Closed until 2036)
Additional scope notes are found at the series level.
Access Restrictions
This collection contains materials protected by attorney-client privilege and, therefore, may be subject to review prior to researcher use. Access to privileged documents will be restricted in compliance with attorney-client confidentiality. Please contact the Archives Service Center for more information.
Acquisition Information
Donated by Susan Brandt, daughter of the Matsons, in June 1984.
Previous Citation
Marjorie and J. Warren Matson Papers, 1942-1980, AIS.1984.17, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Papers of J. Warren Matson, 1942-1977, ais 84:17, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Aged; Aged -- Medical care -- United States; Civil rights; Draft -- United States; Housing -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Juvenile delinquency -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Prisons -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Riots -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Hill District (Pittsburgh, Pa.); Social action; Women; Personal papers; Social workers -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Academic freedom; National Organization for Women; Omrcanin, Ivo; Senior Citizens Services (Pittsburgh, Pa.); Sobell, Morton; University of Pittsburgh; Adams, Harvey; American Civil Liberties Union; Central Committee for Conscientious Objectors; Indiana University of Pennsylvania; Matson, J. Warren
- American Civil Liberties Union (ACLU), Marjorie Matson, 1947-1980; I.
  Scope and Content Notes
  This series contains records of the ACLU at national, state and local levels, including several court cases with which Marjorie Matson was involved. Matson served as the local representative and chair of the Pittsburgh branch in the mid to late 1940s. Ranges of dates are intermittent due to low activity of the Pittsburgh ACLU during and immediately after World War II.
  - ACLU National Organization, 1.
    - Organizational Manual, June 1976 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Board of Directors Minutes, 1947-1977 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence and Memos, 1962-1977 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Position Papers, 1947-1977 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Cooperating Attorneys, June 1, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Cases, 1963-1970 (Box 1, Folder 6-8)
    - Press Releases, 1947-1977 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - News Clippings and Magazine Articles, 1964, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 10-11)
    - Pamphlets (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Publications Lists, 1964-1966 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Testimonies, 1962, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Biennial Conferences, 1968-1976 (Box 1, Folder 15-20)
  - ACLU of Pennsylvania, 2.
    - Organization and By-laws, 1961, 1969, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 1-2)
    - State Board of Directors, 1963-1980 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Executive Committee, 1970-1977 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Budget Committee, 1971-1976 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Various Committees, 1976-1977 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Membership, 1971-1975 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence, 1961-1977 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Legal Docket and Case Status Reports, 1972, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Position Papers, 1963-1977 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Press Releases, 1969-1972 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Newsclippings, 1964-1966 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Memorabilia (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Cases Relating to the Barr-Walker Act, 1960-1967 (Box 2, Folder 14-18)
    - Pa. Defective Delinquent Act / Dallas State Correctional Institute, Dallas, Pa., 1966-1967 (Box 2, Folder 19-21)
    - Dorothy Albert, Progressive Party, Hymen Schlesinger, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - ACLU Pittsburgh Branch, 3.
    - By-laws and Constitution, undated (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Board of Directors, 1971-1980 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Executive Board, 1968-1976 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Executive Committee, 1969-1980 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Executive Committee and Board of Directors Joint Meetings, 1963-1974 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Legal Committee, 1962-1980 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Committee on Civil Liberties in Schools, 1968-1970 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Finance Committee, 1971-1974 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Various Committees, 1969-1976 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Annual Report, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Correspondence, 1972-1980 (Box 2, Folder 33-38)
    - Notes from ACLU Meetings, 1974-1977 (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - Case Status Reports, 1973-1975, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - Carnegie-Illinois Steel Corporation v. United Steel Workers of America, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - Cyrus Wood v. Mount Lebanon Township School District (School Prayer), 1974 (Box 3, Folder 1-2)
    - Hair Cases (High School Dress Codes) (Box 3, Folder 3-4)
    - School Corporal Punishment (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Other Cases (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Statements and Position Papers (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Press Releases (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Newsletters, 1964-1974 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Notices for ACLU Activities (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - News Clippings (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Other Organizations, 4.
    - Other Pennsylvania Branches: Philadelphia, Central, North Central, 1963-1976 (Box 3, Folder 12-13)
    - Other Civil Liberty Organizations, 1964-1974 (Box 3, Folder 14-15)
- Legal Records of Marjorie Matson, 1962-1974; II.
  This series contains records of three cases in which Marjorie Matson was involved as an attorney: a lawsuit against the Pittsburgh Press alleging sex discrimination in employment advertisements (more documentation on this case can be found in the Feminist collection of Joann Evansgardner and Gerald H. F. Gardner, 1966-1988, ais 2001:09); a case challenging as unconstitutional the criminal conviction and sentence of Morton Sobell for an alleged role in the conspiracy of Julius and Ethel Rosenberg; and the tenure case of Dr. Ivo Omrcanin, a professor of Russian at Indiana University of Pennsylvania. Correspondence between Dr. Omrcanin and Matson relating to this case has been closed due to attorney-client privilege: see Series VI. There is also a group of documents from Matson's involvement with various organizations protesting the Vietnam War and the draft.
  - National Organization for Women (NOW) v. the Pittsburgh Press, 1.
    - Pittsburgh Commission on Human Relations, 1969-1970 (Box 3, Folder 16-22)
    - Court of Common Pleas of Allegheny County (Box 3, Folder 23-25)
    - Commonwealth Court of Pa. (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - Supreme Court of the U.S. (Box 3, Folder 27-33)
    - Examples of Ads from Pittsburgh Press (Box 3, Folder 34)
    - Statistics on Women in the Work Force (Box 3, Folder 35)
    - Articles, Writings, News Clippings, 1970-1973 (Box 3, Folder 36-39)
  - Morton Sobell Case, 2.
    - First Appeal, 1962-1963 (Box 4, Folder 1-4)
    - Second Appeal, 1966-1968 (Box 4, Folder 5-6)
    - Case Correspondence, 1962-1968 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Pamphlets (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Tenure Case of Dr. Ivo Omrcanin v. Indiana University of Pennsylvania (IUP), 1968-1974; 3.
    - Credentials and Curriculum Vitae of Dr. Omrcanin (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Ad Hoc Committee of the Faculty Senate, 1968 (Box 4, Folder 10-12)
    - Board of Trustees Hearing, June-July 1969 (Box 4, Folder 13-15)
    - Appeal of Dr. Omrcanin before the Secretary of Education of the Commonwealth of Pa., 1969 (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Court of Common Pleas of Dauphin County, Pa., 1969 (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Commonwealth Court of Pa., 1971-1973 (Box 4, Folder 18-19)
    - Supreme Court of Pa. (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - Grievances of Dr. Omrcanin against the Commonwealth of Pa., Aug 1973 (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - Reports on the Case by IUP Administration (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - Magazine Articles and Clippings (Box 4, Folder 23-24)
    - Various Information about IUP, 1965-1974 (Box 4, Folder 25-26)
  - Vietnam War: Draft Resistance, 4.
    - New York Draft and Military Law Panel, 1968-1969 (Box 4, Folder 27-30)
    - Selective Service Law Panel, Los Angeles, 1969-1971 (Box 4, Folder 31-33)
    - Vietnam Veterans Against the War, Allegheny Region, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 34)
    - Other Organizations, 1969 (Box 4, Folder 35)
    - Documents from Court Cases about the Draft, 1969 (Box 4, Folder 36)
    - News Clippings and Articles, 1965-1968 (Box 4, Folder 37-39)
    - Anti-war Pamphlets (Box 4, Folder 40)
    - Various, 1967, 1969 (Box 4, Folder 41)
- City Development and Housing, J. Warren Matson, III.
  Records in this series document J. Warren Matson's participation in various groups and committees dedicated to planning development of residential areas in the city. There are records of the Housing Authority of the City of Pittsburgh (HACP), the Pittsburgh Model Cities Program, as well as Hill Opportunity, Progress and Education (HOPE) and Transitional Services, Inc., which were founded to advocate and provide for the needs of Hill District residents.
  - Housing Authority of the City of Pittsburgh (HACP), 1.
    - History, 1953, 1959 (Box 4, Folder 42)
    - Correspondence, 1942-1974 (Box 4, Folder 43)
    - Reports and Resolutions, 1946-1975 (Box 4, Folder 44-45)
    - Notes by J. Warren Matson from Meetings, Speeches, etc. (Box 4, Folder 46)
    - Statistics, 1961-1971 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Budget, 1971 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Ancillary Services for the Aged, 1970-1972 (Box 5, Folder 3-11)
    - Contracts, 1971-1972 (Box 5, Folder 12-14)
    - Lower Hill Relocation Project, 1958-1970 (Box 5, Folder 15-17)
    - HACP Member Directory, 1969-1973 (Box 5, Folder 18)
    - Reports, Publications, Clippings, etc., 1942-1971 (Box 5, Folder 19-22)
  - Pittsburgh Model Cities Program, 2.
    - Model Neighborhood Housing Program, 1970 (Box 5, Folder 23)
    - Housing and Land-use Functional Standing Committee, 1968-1975 (Box 5, Folder 24-34)
    - Health and Welfare Functional Standing Committee, 1969-1975 (Box 5, Folder 35-39)
    - Area II: Minutes, Sub-committees and Teams, 1968-1975 (Box 5, Folder 40-45)
    - Area II: Sub-committees and Teams, 1968-1975 (Box 6, Folder 1-3)
    - Model Cities Proposals, Reports, etc., 1968-1976 (Box 6, Folder 4-8)
  - Hill Opportunity, Progress and Education (HOPE), 3.
    - Founding Documents and By-laws, 1976 (Box 6, Folder 9-10)
    - Minutes, 1976-1980 (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Membership, 1976 (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Correspondence (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - Housing and Land Use Committee, 1977 (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - Senior Citizen Program, 1975-1976 (Box 6, Folder 15)
    - Reports on HOPE, 1974-1977 (Box 6, Folder 16-17)
    - Various, 1970-1974 (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Transitional Services, Inc., 4.
    - Founding Documents, 1969-1970 (Box 6, Folder 19)
    - Minutes: Board of Directors Meetings, 1974-1980 (Box 6, Folder 20)
    - Finance Committee, 1976-1980 (Box 6, Folder 21)
    - Other Committees, 1977-1980 (Box 6, Folder 22)
    - Membership, 1970-1971, 1977-1980 (Box 6, Folder 23)
    - Correspondence, 1969, 1977, 1979 (Box 6, Folder 24)
    - Reports, 1969-1979 (Box 6, Folder 25-29)
    - Publications, 1968, 1977-1979 (Box 6, Folder 30)
    - Housing Facilities Inc.: By-laws, Feb 1973 (Box 6, Folder 31)
    - Minutes: Transitional Services, Inc., Housing Corporation, 1972 (Box 6, Folder 32)
    - Board of Directors, 1973-1978 (Box 6, Folder 33)
    - Various Committees, 1973-1975 (Box 6, Folder 34)
    - Lists of Board of Directors, 1973-1978 (Box 6, Folder 35)
    - Correspondence, 1973-1977 (Box 6, Folder 36)
    - Audit Reports, 1974-1975 (Box 6, Folder 37)
    - Financial Information, 1973-1978 (Box 6, Folder 38)
    - Information Bulletin, Housing Facilities, Inc., with drafts, Feb 1975 (Box 6, Folder 39)
    - Available Apartments (Box 6, Folder 40)
    - Examples of Leases (Box 6, Folder 41)
- Other Civic Involvement of J. Warren Matson, IV.
  J. Warren Matson was active in other community groups, which are represented in this series: Action Coalition of Elders, which he helped to establish, the Committee to Improve Kane Hospital, and the development committees of the Carnegie Library and the YMCA at Center Avenue. There is also some material relating to the Southwest Pennsylvania Chapter of the National Association of Social Workers.
  - Action Coalition of Elders (ACE), 1.
    - Founding Documents, 1975-1976 (Box 6, Folder 42-43)
    - Minutes and Agendas, 1977-1978 (Box 6, Folder 44-48)
    - Correspondence, 1975-1978 (Box 6, Folder 49)
    - Personnel and Membership (Box 6, Folder 50-51)
    - Reports about ACE (Box 6, Folder 52)
    - Financial Information, 1976-1976 (Box 6, Folder 53)
    - Notes by J. Warren Matson from Meetings, etc. (Box 6, Folder 54)
    - Tell-A-Phone (TAP) Poll (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - League of Voting Elders (LOVE) (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Pamphlets on ACE and Senior Citizens (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - News Clippings (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Conferences on the Elderly, 1975, 1978 (Box 7, Folder 5-6)
    - Various (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Kane Hospital Improvement, 2.
    - Committee to Improve Kane Hospital: By-Laws, Minutes, and Correspondence, 1975-1978 (Box 7, Folder 8-11)
    - Kane Hospital Information (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - Membership List of Kane Hospital Task Force and Supporting Organizations (Box 7, Folder 13)
    - Kane Hospital Newsletters, Pamphlets, and News Clippings, 1976-1978 (Box 7, Folder 14-15)
  - General Civil Improvement, 3.
    - Young Men's Christian Association (YMCA) of Pittsburgh, 1966-1976 (Box 7, Folder 16-17)
    - Hill District Recreation Agencies, 1971-1972 (Box 7, Folder 18)
    - Mercy Hospital Neighborhood Committee on Health Care, 1968-1979 (Box 7, Folder 19-25)
    - Wylie Avenue Library Advisory Committee, 1975-1977 (Box 7, Folder 26)
    - Cost of Living, 1960-1978 (Box 7, Folder 27)
    - Housing Laws, 1949-1968 (Box 7, Folder 28)
    - National Association of Social Workers (NASW), Southwest Pa. Chapter, 1955-1976 (Box 7, Folder 29)
- Subject Files, V.
  These files consist mostly of reports on a variety of subjects similar to those represented elsewhere in the collection, such as housing, civil rights, and urban planning.
  - Housing Inadequacies Task Force Report, 1971 (Box 7, Folder 30)
  - Pittsburgh Bicentennial, 1958 (Box 7, Folder 31-32)
  - Pittsburgh Public Schools Discipline Code and Procedures, 1971 (Box 7, Folder 33)
  - Police-Community Relations, 1973 (Box 7, Folder 34)
  - Racial Disorder in Pittsburgh (Box 7, Folder 35)
  - Ross Township, Pa. (Box 7, Folder 36)
  - Brady Street Bridge, 1970, 1972 (Box 7, Folder 37)
  - Urban Redevelopment Authority of Pittsburgh, 1968 (Box 7, Folder 38)
  - Watts Labor Community Action Committee, Los Angeles, Ca., 1967 (Box 7, Folder 39)
  - Health and Welfare Planning Association, 1977-1978 (Box 7, Folder 40)
- Client Files of Marjorie Matson, VI.; [RESTRICTED]
  These files contain notes taken by Marjorie Matson during her arguing of cases, as well as correspondence related to various cases in which she was involved. The files of correspondence include many letters from clients, potential clients, and families of clients, often relating to imprisonment, mental illness, and other sensitive details, as well as private documents like birth certificates. In the interest of protecting privacy and honoring attorney-client privilege, these records are closed to researchers until 2036. Case-related correspondence which does not contain privileged information is found in Series I and II.
  - Case Notes and Correspondence, [RESTRICTED] (Box 8)